WORK EXPERIENCE

JANUARY 2022 - PRESENT

Sr. Data Scientist, DCCA

Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve

Part-time rotation focused on proactively identifying potential risks to consumer financial health.

- Developed early warning metrics on the automotive and credit card market to proactively identify recessions; presented work to committee comprised of the governors
- Reconciled data source from various vendors and regulatory reporting to calibrate an accurate picture of the economy
- Collaborated across different groups (CCA, Supervisory, Payment Systems) on various AI topics and their potential harms to the consumer

Sr. Data Scientist, FedNow Federal Reserve Bank of Boston

Designer and architect behind the first AI systems for fraud detection on the FedNow Service

- Developed FedNow AAT and Network Intelligence service in collaboration with vendor partners, technology, audit and program management.
- Lead a team of 20 in a hackthon to produce first ever cross-rail payments fraud model
- Lead a cross-functional team to develop model validation, data privacy, and other data governance output for the Federal Reserve Financial Services

AUGUST- 2018 - DECEMBER 2021

Chief Data Scientist, Atlanta TSYS, a Global Payments Company

Created first Data Science team and overall Research and Development program within TSYS. Primary focus is in Fraud & Risk with mandate to develop into other portfolio areas.

- Established program, team, and platform for rapid data science innovation Retooled for a consulting service with \$2M annual run rate.
- Developed industry leading model, TSYS Foresight Score as the primary data scientist and moved into production for 30+ different financial institutions and over \$10M in revenue
- Designed and constructed the TSYS R&D Data Lake at a total cost of \$300K - by far the single most efficient asset in TSYS history with \$2.5M USD in realized income

PUBLICATIONS

"Methods, Systems, and Apparatuses for improved fraud detection and reduction" U.S. Pat. US 2021/0042824A1" USPTO

______https://patents.google.com/patent/ US20210042824A1 Thomas Tarler Falmouth, ME +1 (720)496-9222 ttarler@gmail.com

SUMMARY

A top data scientist in banking and payments with experience in acquiring and issuing and an expert in fraud and real time authorizations, FedNow, and other government payment systems as well as as BSA/AML. I regularly transform limited budgets and informal influence into tightly focused projects with very large ROI. Skilled communicator, seller, leader, and visionary - I build teams, platforms, and processes for success in Artificial Intelligence.

EDUCATION

2011 - 2015 Bachelor of Arts

With Distinction and Cum Laude MATHMEMATICS AND ECONOMICS University of Denver

2017 - 2020 **Master of Science**

DATA SCIENCE, WITH HONORS Regis University

TECHNICAL SKILLS

Clearances

Techniques	Machine learning, Deep Reinforcment Learning, DevOps, Agile, financial forecasting, reinforcement/policy learning, data visualization, data wrangling, anomaly detection, data mining, event streaming, risk estimation and optimization
Technology	SQL, PYTHON, R, Tableau, Hadoop, Spark, big data, mainframes, non-stop systems, ERP

ĆSI/FOMC Level 3 (SF85-P),

FedNow Moderate (SF-84)